Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Engineering Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Civil Engineering
    - AlMansoori, Maryam, James Gardner, and Paul Ha. Water Treatment Facility in the Northern Emirates, 2017; 2017-0012; Maryam AlMansoori, James Gardner: The Northern Emirates faces unique and challenging water resourcing; with some of the most limited availability in ground water, and a water usa
      Abstract, Paul Ha: The UAE must have highly efficient waste water recycling systems. This project outlines a recycled wastewater treatment facility treating 225,000 m3 of water per day located in the Northern Emirates. The scope of the design includes the water treatment process, structural housing, and road access with parking facilities. This document includes design drawings and analysis alongside project management methods undertaken to complete the project. The design chosen is a multistage water treatment process modelled on a traditional sewage treatment plant; wastewater undergoes primary, secondary and tertiary treatment in the form of coagulation, flocculation and sedimentation, a plug flow reactivated sludge line, and dual media filtration plus UV treatment. These processes were selected as best practices across the industry. Treated water is at a standard to allow for restricted irrigation as per the Dubai Municipality codes. This water is ready for distribution and use for irrigation in non-raw crops and landscaping. Designs were carried out in accordance with the Abu Dhabi Municipal Standards, the Dubai Municipality Standards, Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), American Society of Civil Engineering (ASCE), the American Concrete Institute (ACI) and the American Institute of Steel Construction (AISC) codes.
    - Abdelkhalek, Hassan, and Noor Ehab Alameri. Sustainable Low-income Housing Design, 2018; 2018-0047; The project had two main objectives which were to produce a low cost and sustainable design for a 1 story house in Abu Dhabi. Through extensive research, material testing and conscious architectural design which efficiently uses the space allocated to the project these two objectives were met. The proposed house design costs 47% less than an average house of a similar size in the USA, excluding labor cost since it varies greatly across the world. Moreover, the materials proposed and tested provide a more sustainable and low cost alternative to the conventional building materials used. Not only do they decrease the running costs of the house, but they also reduce the amount of energy consumed by the household mainly through decreasing cooling costs. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0047)
      The project had two main objectives which were to produce a low cost and sustainable design for a 1 story house in Abu Dhabi. Through extensive research, material testing and conscious architectural design which efficiently uses the space allocated to the project these two objectives were met. The proposed house design costs 47% less than an average house of a similar size in the USA, excluding labor cost since it varies greatly across the world. Moreover, the materials proposed and tested provide a more sustainable and low cost alternative to the conventional building materials used. Not only do they decrease the running costs of the house, but they also reduce the amount of energy consumed by the household mainly through decreasing cooling costs.
    - Ivanov, Petar; Chandan Mishra, and Jagan Narayanan Subramanian. Design of a 3-Story Educational Building with Ultra-Lightweight Cement Composite, 2019; 2019-0052 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0055)
      The increasing costs in all aspects of manufacturing have led to significant increase in construction costs. This, alongside with a number of environmental concerns over the traditional construction practices, calls for an active investigation in new and innovative ways of designing structures. This project aims to design a modern educational building that is both cost-efficient and environmentally friendly. The proposed design integrates innovative materials and advanced building Science concepts and techniques that ensure a sustainable and efficient design. An well-planned design allows for the seamless integration of elements that allow light and natural air circulation as well as a comfortable interaction with the surrounding environment landscape. Thus, comfortable study conditions for the occupants are met while boosting the building performance and minimizing its carbon footprint. With this in mind, the project aims to explore the use of EPS beads in ultra-lightweight concrete composite as the theoretical analysis suggests better thermal performance of the building.
    - Khan, Waqar Younas, and Abdur (Mani) Rehman. Room Design for Effective Evacuation under Escape Panic, 2019; 2019-0058 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0058)
      The standards of evacuation design have not changed much in the past half a century. Any progress that is being made is so insignificant in value that the adoption of the ideas globally is not a priority. The 21st century is about minute detail optimization to achieve maximum efficiency. It is this search that is explained in the capstone where we try and understand the details and try to morph obstacles so as to help us achieve designs that lead to the goals we have set. In order to do this, inspiration from Dirk Helbing's work from 2001 was taken that discusses the possibility of improving evacuation rates by introducing obstacles in the pathway of an exit. The project delves further into this concept by trying to employ one or all of the following; deep neural networks, reinforced learning, and VISSIM. Based on the results obtained by Helbing, we expect that there is a certain design of obstacles that can improve the flow of pedestrians in an emergency evacuation. To answer this question, our research found that introducing funnel-shaped exits with a central kite-shaped obstacle produce the most efficient room design for evacuation.
    - Okoth, Victor, Raitis Pekuss, and Ylber Roka. Analysis of PWPB Algorithm for Incremental CAV Market Penetration Rates, 2019; 2019-0048 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0048)
      Connected and Autonomous Vehicles are widely expected to revolutionize urban transportation. Their increased presence is expected to mitigate traffic congestions, environmental hazards presented by vehicles, reduce the number of accidents while also increasing the throughput of traffic networks. However, these benefits will become apparent gradually corresponding to the gradual market penetration rates of CAVs. This paper studies traffic intersection control of mixed vehicle traffic that consists of CAVs as well as human driven vehicles. Specifically, we analyze the Position Back Pressure algorithm which is studied to outperform SCOOT - a widely accepted real-time adaptive traffic control method - in terms of delays for both low and high demand traffic conditions. We address the underlying assumption in the algorithm that all the information about vehicles in the network is known. Such a scenario is only possible with a 100% market penetration of CAVs and, therefore, does not reflect the real life conditions. To address this we vary the amount of known and, consequently, estimated data, which is then fed into the traffic simulation. As the result of this we can understand how sensitive is PWBP to inputs with varying levels of real and estimated data.
  - Computer Engineering
    - Alfergani, Noha H. Design of an Automatic Test Pattern Generation Tool for VLSI Transition Faults, 2015; 2015-0030 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0030)
      Major: Computer Engineering
      Abstract: Integrated circuits are extensively and universally utilized. Their applications vary from consumer products to mission critical electronics, creating a spectrum of susceptibility towards defects that accompany the manufacturing process. Thus, each electronic chip undergoes testing that determines whether the chip is defective or defect-free upon being manufactured. The testing process encompasses the application of carefully selected test patterns that produce an output which is observed and compared to an expected output. There are number of fault models that guide the testing process. This project aims to create an Automatic Test Pattern Generation Tool, a software tool, targeting the transition delay fault model. The test patterns generated by the software tool will then be used in the hardware component of the project. The test patterns will be applied to a desired circuit uploaded to an FPGA board to verify the output responses. The output will be verified by observing the output response to the expected output given the circuit under test. This is the test application phase of the project.
      Testing chips; Transitional delay faults; Computer engineering; Automatic Test Pattern Generation (ATPG)
    - Chen, Jeffrey. Towards the Design of Intelligent 3D Computer Vision, 2015; 2015-0026 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0026)
      Abstract: This capstone project aims to design an intelligent framework for addressing such challenging issues from ever-growing 3D datasets. We intend to develop a system that takes 3D objects and presents them in various robust analytical models. Specifically, the proposed framework seeks to develop a cohesive and consistent shape analysis pipeline system that can correctly identify and preserve the important features of shapes. These important shape features will be processed and modelled into shape correspondences for 3D shapes registration, shape descriptors to evaluate the geometric similarities between shapes for 3D shape retrieval, and a clustering paradigm for discerning parts for 3D shape segmentation. The overall shape analysis pipeline is intended to deliver a standard process for capturing 3D object information from different analytical perspectives for further field-specific interests, such as categorization, detection, and representation. These perspectives are based in one-to-one, one-to-all, and introspective object comparisons that provide deep yet generally important understanding of shape features, opening them to further studies in matching, relating, and labelling.
      Computer engineering; Geometry; 3D
    - Alhosani, Hamdan Ahmed, and Hazem Ibrahim. SFLL-HD Logic Locking Framework, 2018; 2018-0044; IC netlists are valuable assets by nature since it holds the basic design of electronic chips. However, the process of manufacturing chips is complicated as there are multiple threats from untrusted users and fabricators. Logic Locking has been perceived as a promising and reliable defense mechanism against intellectual property piracy, reverse engineering and overbuilding attacks. Stripped Functionality Logic Locking, or SFLL, is proven to be resilient to all types of hardware attacks on a netlist in the paper Provably Secure Logic Locking: From Theory To Practice. [1] SFLL strips some of the functionality of the circuit and hides it in the form of a secret key(s). Thereby, rendering the on-chip implementation functionally different than the original netlist. Currently, implementing any logic locking framework on a given netlist is complicated. In this paper, we propose a software framework that implements SFLL on any Verilog netlist. The software will produce a secured netlist that can thwart multiple attacks such as, SAT attack, removal attack and sanitization attack. In addition, verification of the correct implementation of SFLL security will be completed to ensure the validity of the software framework. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0044)
      IC netlists are valuable assets by nature since it holds the basic design of electronic chips. However, the process of manufacturing chips is complicated as there are multiple threats from untrusted users and fabricators. Logic Locking has been perceived as a promising and reliable defense mechanism against intellectual property piracy, reverse engineering and overbuilding attacks. Stripped Functionality Logic Locking, or SFLL, is proven to be resilient to all types of hardware attacks on a netlist in the paper Provably Secure Logic Locking: From Theory To Practice. [1] SFLL strips some of the functionality of the circuit and hides it in the form of a secret key(s). Thereby, rendering the on-chip implementation functionally different than the original netlist. Currently, implementing any logic locking framework on a given netlist is complicated. In this paper, we propose a software framework that implements SFLL on any Verilog netlist. The software will produce a secured netlist that can thwart multiple attacks such as, SAT attack, removal attack and sanitization attack. In addition, verification of the correct implementation of SFLL security will be completed to ensure the validity of the software framework.
    - Farhan, Yasmin and Christos Zoukos. A Portable Supercomputer, 2018; 2018-0037; Supercomputers, while powerful and useful for intensive computing operations, are also extremely expensive with high power demands. Combining the processing power of these power efficient, low cost, 4 core, ARM processor based Raspberry Pi computers will allow for an investigation into creating a cheaper and more power efficient alternative. Mounting this cluster onto a portable iRobot base will allow for valuable information to be gleaned about the tradeoff between power consumption and performance. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0037)
      Supercomputers, while powerful and useful for intensive computing operations, are also extremely expensive with high power demands. Combining the processing power of these power efficient, low cost, 4 core, ARM processor based Raspberry Pi computers will allow for an investigation into creating a cheaper and more power efficient alternative. Mounting this cluster onto a portable iRobot base will allow for valuable information to be gleaned about the tradeoff between power consumption and performance.
    - AlHarmoodi, Mariam. Hardware Accelerator for Visual Memory Reconstruction, 2019; 2019-0061 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0061)
      In the field of neuroScience, there has been recent research on the reconstruction of visual working memory during the representation of items from the activity of neuronal populations, particularly focusing on oscillatory activity in the alpha band (8-12 Hz). The objective of this project is a real time (i.e., less than 500ms) functional hardware implementation of memory reconstruction by feeding Magnetoencephalography (MEG) or electroencephalography (EEG) of neural oscillations to a Nexys 4 Artix-7 Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) Trainer Board. This can be realized by converting the time-series to frequencies in the alpha region. In this proposal, a Hilbert transform with an iterative-pipelined hybrid architecture is chosen to achieve the most optimal results in terms of speed, complexity, and available hardware resources amongst various other solutions.
    - Gamil, Homer, and Steffen Holter. Data Visualization and Feature Extraction, 2019; 2019-0050 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0050)
      Advancements in the field of big data have brought on the need for new tools to understand the underlying properties of all this information. Data visualization presents one of the most productive ways of tackling this problem. Our solution focuses on extracting the key features that effectively describe the dataset and visualizing this information on an interactive display.The fundamental aspect of this design is creating a means for high performance dimensionality reduction. Whilst many solutions exist that use principle component analysis (PCA) or non-parametric algorithms, they struggle with generalizing to more complex manifolds and sparse data. Therefore, our approach instead makes use of a deep learning architecture. By creating a complex neural network hierarchy, we aim to optimize the solution and create a data describing mapping that corresponds to the intrinsic dimensionality of the data itself.
  - Electrical Engineering
    - Aujeszky, Tamas. Design of Arabic Sign Language Interpreter Using Microsoft Kinect, 2014; 2014-0039 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0039)
      Major: Electrical Engineering
      Abstract: This final report is made for the Senior Capstone Design Project of New York University Abu Dhabi. It outlines a proposed solution to overcome a large part of the difficulties that hearing-impaired people face when they need to communicate. As a second benefit, the solution also facilitates education of sign-language. It also contains information related to the progress in implementing the solution.
      Currently there are no affordable solutions on the market, and previous results are either lacking in quality or highly limited in usability. With the help of the next generation of hardware sensors, the proposed solution is aimed to greatly improve on these shortcomings while bearing an affordable price tag. In addition, the proposed solution is the first known of its kind that focuses on Arabic sign language, an area where current awareness is low and the room for improvement is vast.
      The solution consists of an affordable hardware sensor available on the market and software algorithms designed in order to process the data acquired by the sensor. Together they set up a system that is robust, user-friendly and also possesses the potential for a wide reach through its low price point.
      Schools/Education; Hearing impairments; Disabilities; Communication; Sign language; Kinect (Programmable controller); Electrical engineering
    - Abe, Yilkal. FPGA Based Network for Fast Microprocessor Simulation, 2016; 2016-0026; Simulation and verification are important stages in the manufacturing of modern day microprocessors. As digital design systems increase in complexity, the task of running an effective software simulation of these systems becomes computationally expensive and prohibitive. Such designs contain billions of transistors, while a typical workload executes in several million-clock cycles. Thus, workload software simulation to completion is infeasible in lower levels of abstraction. In order to bypass the slow software simulation speed, a simulation using a network of FPGAs is proposed. FPGAs are reconfigurable devices that can implement a digital design. They have hardware speed and reliability and don't incur on the large price required for ASIC design. This makes FPGAs ideal for implementing simulation of digital devices. However, the size of the digital design that each FPGA can simulate depends on the limited number of configurable blocks available and the total number of IO located on its banks. In this project, a network of FPGAs will be developed that will efficiently simulate a modern microprocessor. A scalable system was built and a simulation speed up of 20x software simulation has been achieved. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0026)
      Simulation and verification are important stages in the manufacturing of modern day microprocessors. As digital design systems increase in complexity, the task of running an effective software simulation of these systems becomes computationally expensive and prohibitive. Such designs contain billions of transistors, while a typical workload executes in several million-clock cycles. Thus, workload software simulation to completion is infeasible in lower levels of abstraction. In order to bypass the slow software simulation speed, a simulation using a network of FPGAs is proposed. FPGAs are reconfigurable devices that can implement a digital design. They have hardware speed and reliability and don't incur on the large price required for ASIC design. This makes FPGAs ideal for implementing simulation of digital devices. However, the size of the digital design that each FPGA can simulate depends on the limited number of configurable blocks available and the total number of IO located on its banks. In this project, a network of FPGAs will be developed that will efficiently simulate a modern microprocessor. A scalable system was built and a simulation speed up of 20x software simulation has been achieved.
    - Pacareu, Pablo, and Pedro Gaizka Zufiria Gerboles. Development of a Red-Team-In-a-Box hardware platform, 2017; 2017-0014; The modernization of critical infrastructure has enabled advanced monitoring and control capabilities, through the inclusion of microprocessor computing systems using commercial-off-the-shelf integrated circuits and commonly used protocols. Therefore, these systems are susceptible to cyber-attacks. The aim of the project was to identify possible entry points in order to fortify said systems. An advanced sensing platform was developed, which could facilitate physical penetration testing of industrial control systems. The platform had its own processing capabilities and operated on a battery in order to achieve autonomy. The sensors used were integrated on a custom-built PCB. The goal was to maximize the information collected by the platform, while minimizing the power consumption and the cost. The resulting platform was able to fingerprint industrial devices, eavesdrop on communications and collect other information needed to generate a detailed map of the surrounding environment of the industrial control system. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0014)
      The modernization of critical infrastructure has enabled advanced monitoring and control capabilities, through the inclusion of microprocessor computing systems using commercial-off-the-shelf integrated circuits and commonly used protocols. Therefore, these systems are susceptible to cyber-attacks. The aim of the project was to identify possible entry points in order to fortify said systems. An advanced sensing platform was developed, which could facilitate physical penetration testing of industrial control systems. The platform had its own processing capabilities and operated on a battery in order to achieve autonomy. The sensors used were integrated on a custom-built PCB. The goal was to maximize the information collected by the platform, while minimizing the power consumption and the cost. The resulting platform was able to fingerprint industrial devices, eavesdrop on communications and collect other information needed to generate a detailed map of the surrounding environment of the industrial control system.
    - Rudchenko, Vasily, and Martin Slosarik. Design of Secure and Testable Chips, 2017; 2017-0020; Integrated circuit production facilities cost upward of $1billion to build and maintain, which is why semiconductor companies are shifting into a more effective fabless model. In this system, chip designers create circuit floorplans, but do not manufacture the chips in house. Instead, external foundries produce the chip. The purpose of the capstone project was to conduct an implementation from RTL to silicon, while addressing concerns of a fabless design process. As most chip foundries are substitutable, the IP of chip designs is the core value driver in the industry. Thus, the project focused on integrating new functionalities with an existing design of an ARM CortexM0 chip. To ensure that the chip is easily testable after manufacturing, we enriched it with a JTAG test module for functional and scan chain testing. Since providing the chip design to foundries around the world raises concerns about illegal chip overproduction and tampering, we applied the SARLock logic encryption method. Lastly, we conducted rigorous physical implementation. We implemented the physical chip from the RTL description of the ARM CortexM0 Microprocessor to the GDSII format. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0020)